<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Saurav Kumar Roy</title><link>https://Sauravroy34.github.io/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Saurav Kumar Roy</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 00:32:11 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://Sauravroy34.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Jwst Light Curve and Planet Spectra</title><link>https://Sauravroy34.github.io/posts/jwst-light-curve-and-planet-spectra/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 00:32:11 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://Sauravroy34.github.io/posts/jwst-light-curve-and-planet-spectra/</guid><description>&lt;h3 id="wasp-39b-light-curve-and-planet-spectra">Wasp-39b light curve and planet spectra&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Recenly i made a cool project where i plot the light curve of star WASP-39 where its exoplanet hot jupyter was also witnessed As per nasa data &lt;a href="https://exoplanetarchive.ipac.caltech.edu/overview/WASP-39#planet_WASP-39-b_collapsible">wasp-39b&lt;/a>! WASP-39b has a mass of about 0.28 times that of Jupiter and a radius about 1.27 times that of Jupiter (91,000 km) It is a hot gas giant planet with a high temperature of 900 °C. The exoplanet orbits very close (7 million km) to WASP-39, its host star, every 4 days. In addition WASP-39b was the first exoplanet found to contain carbon dioxide in its atmosphere,and likewise for sulfur dioxide.WASP-39b is in the constellation Virgo, and is about 700 light-years from Earth. As part of the NameExoWorlds campaigns at the 100th anniversary of the IAU, the planet was named Bocaprins, after the beach Boca Prins in the Arikok National Park of Aruba.The star which this planet is orbiting around is WASP-39&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="now-what-is-light-curve-">Now what is light curve ?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>I wont go into details but light curve are a plot of incoming photons count or flux vs time so basically its a plot which shows how much light is coming for given period(which is called exposure) it is observed by a telescope which stares a star one of the cool things about light curves are that one can find and discover exoplanet check this out for more detail &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Methods_of_detecting_exoplanets#Transit_photometry">Transit-photometry&lt;/a>!&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="what-are-planet-spectra-">What are planet spectra ?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Telescope which uses &lt;a href="https://noirlab.edu/public/blog/50-years-ccds/">CCD&lt;/a>! provides the ability to user to know the photons arrival time, its energy and counts too through this knowledge one can easily plot the planet spectra which is nothing but plot of flux or photon counts vs the wavelength band &lt;a href="https://oxfordre.com/planetaryscience/display/10.1093/acrefore/9780190647926.001.0001/acrefore-9780190647926-e-134">Planet Spectroscopy&lt;/a>!&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="datasets-and-project-implementation">Datasets and project implementation&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Datasets was gathered from James webb telescope NIRSpec instrument which was in BOTS mode for more detail check this out &lt;a href="https://jwst-docs.stsci.edu/jwst-near-infrared-spectrograph/nirspec-observing-modes/nirspec-bright-object-time-series-spectroscopy#gsc.tab=0">NIRSpec-Bright-Object-Time-Series-Spectroscopy&lt;/a>! dataset was download from &lt;a href="https://mast.stsci.edu/portal/Mashup/Clients/Mast/Portal.html">MAST&lt;/a>! portal and all the files were in &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FITS">fits&lt;/a>! format which is the most popular in astronomy&lt;/p>
&lt;p>project is made in jupyter notebook and here are some of the intresting plots&lt;/p>
&lt;h4 id="light-curve-and-poission-regression-fit">Light curve and poission regression fit&lt;/h4>
&lt;h4 id="planet-spectra">Planet spectra&lt;/h4>
&lt;h3 id="finally-the-project-repo-link">finally the project repo link&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The project can be found in my github repo &lt;a href="https://github.com/Sauravroy34/JWST-light-curve-and-spectral-analysis">JWST-light-curve-and-Planet-spectra&lt;/a>!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>My Open Source Journey</title><link>https://Sauravroy34.github.io/posts/my-open-source-journey/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 16:00:58 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://Sauravroy34.github.io/posts/my-open-source-journey/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="my-open-source-journey">My Open Source Journey&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s been around &lt;strong>8 months&lt;/strong> since I started contributing to &lt;strong>open source&lt;/strong>, beginning with &lt;a href="https://openastronomy.org/">OpenAstronomy&lt;/a>!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>OpenAstronomy is an umbrella organization, and within it, I am an active contributor to:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://github.com/sunpy/sunpy">SunPy&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://github.com/StingraySoftware/stingray">Stingray Software&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="an-incredible-journey-so-far">An Incredible Journey So Far&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>This journey has been &lt;strong>amazing&lt;/strong>! I&amp;rsquo;ve had the opportunity to interact with incredible people—some are &lt;strong>researchers&lt;/strong>, some work at &lt;strong>NASA&lt;/strong> and &lt;strong>ESA&lt;/strong>, and others are &lt;strong>professors at top universities&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Through open source, I&amp;rsquo;ve learned &lt;strong>a lot&lt;/strong> about:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Computational Astronomy&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Coding Standards&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Unit Testing with &lt;code>pytest&lt;/code>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Documentation with &lt;code>Sphinx&lt;/code>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Pre-commit Hooks&lt;/li>
&lt;li>learned how to work with File formats like &lt;code>FITS&lt;/code> and &lt;code>ASDF&lt;/code>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>By the way i got into open source around september 2024 and journey has been amazing so far!!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>My First Post</title><link>https://Sauravroy34.github.io/posts/my-first-post/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 15:57:50 +0530</pubDate><guid>https://Sauravroy34.github.io/posts/my-first-post/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hi I am Saurav Kumar Roy a undergrad student from Amrita Viswa Vidyapeetham Amritapuri in India and This is my new blogging site. I will be posting my journey and experiences here. Enjoy!&amp;quot;&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>