<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Saurav Kumar Roy</title>
    <link>https://Sauravroy34.github.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Saurav Kumar Roy</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 18:37:50 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://Sauravroy34.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting Up HEASOFT</title>
      <link>https://Sauravroy34.github.io/posts/setting-up-heasoft/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 18:37:50 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://Sauravroy34.github.io/posts/setting-up-heasoft/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;setting-up-heasoft-a-frustrating-but-rewarding-experience&#34;&gt;Setting Up HEASOFT: A Frustrating but Rewarding Experience&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First of all, I had no idea that setting up HEASOFT would be &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; painful. The official documentation didn’t help much, and I needed HEASOFT for my GSoC project with Stingray, where it’s used for Level 1 data processing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-heasoft&#34;&gt;What is HEASOFT?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;HEASoft (High Energy Astrophysics Software) is a unified package that includes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FTOOLS&lt;/strong&gt;: Tools to manipulate FITS files, both general-purpose and mission-specific.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;XANADU&lt;/strong&gt;: A set of high-level, multi-mission tasks for analyzing X-ray spectral, timing, and imaging data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and lot more !!!
It bundles everything you need to work with X-ray astronomical data. You can download either the source code or precompiled executables depending on your system. It even has a web-based interface called &lt;a href=&#34;https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/sciserver/&#34;&gt;sciserver&lt;/a&gt;!.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-i-finally-got-heasoft-to-work&#34;&gt;How I Finally Got HEASOFT to Work&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The official documentation didn’t really help me much, so I had to hunt around online. Thankfully, I found an amazing YouTube channel: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/@nspace-cowboy&#34;&gt;Nick Space Cowboy&lt;/a&gt;! He has a complete, step-by-step guide on installing HEASOFT, and following it made the process &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; much easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took about an hour to fully install everything, and to my surprise, he also had tutorials on analyzing NICER data, which is super helpful for my project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, I’ve managed to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set up HEASOFT successfully&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Configure the NICER CALDB (Calibration Database)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add geomagnetic files required for preprocessing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re struggling like I was, I &lt;em&gt;highly&lt;/em&gt; recommend checking out Nick’s channel. It might save you hours of frustration.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GSoC Proposal</title>
      <link>https://Sauravroy34.github.io/posts/gsoc-proposal/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 12:40:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://Sauravroy34.github.io/posts/gsoc-proposal/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been around 8 months since I discovered the Stingray project. My first pull request to the Stingray software involved implementing &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/StingraySoftware/stingray/pull/847&#34;&gt;pre-commit hooks&lt;/a&gt;, which was merged on September 30, 2024. Since then, I’ve found this package fascinating and have contributed a few more PRs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before this, I didn’t know about Stingray or even the role of Python in astronomy. To be honest, learning how the package works was overwhelming at first, but the journey has been incredibly rewarding. Here&amp;rsquo;s what I’ve learned so far:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The physics of black holes and X-ray binaries&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How light curves and power spectra are used in analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Various statistical and signal processing methods like correlation and Fourier transforms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Different states of black holes and the radio jets they emit during transitions from soft to hard states (and vice versa)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tools used in astronomy like HEASOFT&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How CCDs in telescopes work, and much more&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m proud that I was able to learn all of this while still pursuing my B.Tech!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;gsoc-project&#34;&gt;GSoC Project&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project I&amp;rsquo;m interested in is &lt;a href=&#34;https://openastronomy.org/gsoc/gsoc2025/#/projects?project=interactive_database_for_x-ray_observations&#34;&gt;Interactive Database for X-ray Binary Observations&lt;/a&gt;, a 350-hour GSoC project. The goal is to build a catalog of black hole binaries where users can track their evolution using a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/figure/The-hardness-intensity-diagram-showing-the-added-information-gained-when-including-the_fig1_230595369#:~:text=The%20hardness%2Dintensity%20diagram%20showing%20the%20added%20information%20gained%20when,and%20darker%20to%20lower%20flux.&#34;&gt;Hardness-Intensity Diagram (HID)&lt;/a&gt;—a plot showing photon intensity and the ratio of counts across specific energy bands (e.g., [2–4 keV]/[4–12 keV]).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The database would include Fourier and timing products like light curves, power spectra, and energy spectra for each observation. Currently, most analyses focus on individual observations, which is useful for estimating spin and mass, but this project aims to provide a complete overview of a black hole&amp;rsquo;s evolution over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;my-proposal&#34;&gt;My Proposal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After two months of trial and error—learning, exploring, and refining—the proposal is finally ready! This is my first time writing such a detailed technical document. I plan to submit it soon, as the deadline is April 8, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fingers crossed! Let&amp;rsquo;s hope for the best! 🙌&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>JWST Light Curve and Planet Spectra</title>
      <link>https://Sauravroy34.github.io/posts/jwst-light-curve-and-planet-spectra/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 00:32:11 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://Sauravroy34.github.io/posts/jwst-light-curve-and-planet-spectra/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;wasp-39b-light-curve-and-planet-spectra&#34;&gt;WASP-39b Light Curve and Planet Spectra&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, I worked on a cool project where I plotted the light curve of the star &lt;strong&gt;WASP-39&lt;/strong&gt;, during which its exoplanet — the hot Jupiter &lt;strong&gt;WASP-39b&lt;/strong&gt; — was also observed. According to &lt;a href=&#34;https://exoplanetarchive.ipac.caltech.edu/overview/WASP-39#planet_WASP-39-b_collapsible&#34;&gt;NASA&amp;rsquo;s exoplanet archive&lt;/a&gt;, WASP-39b has about &lt;strong&gt;0.28 times the mass of Jupiter&lt;/strong&gt; and a &lt;strong&gt;radius 1.27 times that of Jupiter&lt;/strong&gt; (~91,000 km).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a hot gas giant with a scorching temperature of around &lt;strong&gt;900 °C&lt;/strong&gt;. The planet orbits very close to its host star (about &lt;strong&gt;7 million km away&lt;/strong&gt;) and completes one orbit in just &lt;strong&gt;4 days&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WASP-39b was the &lt;strong&gt;first exoplanet discovered to contain carbon dioxide in its atmosphere&lt;/strong&gt;, and sulfur dioxide was also detected. It lies in the &lt;strong&gt;Virgo&lt;/strong&gt; constellation and is about &lt;strong&gt;700 light-years away&lt;/strong&gt; from Earth. As part of the NameExoWorlds campaign for the IAU’s 100th anniversary, the planet was officially named &lt;strong&gt;Bocaprins&lt;/strong&gt;, after &lt;em&gt;Boca Prins&lt;/em&gt; beach in Aruba’s Arikok National Park. The star it orbits is &lt;strong&gt;WASP-39&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-is-a-light-curve&#34;&gt;What Is a Light Curve?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In simple terms, a &lt;strong&gt;light curve&lt;/strong&gt; is a plot of incoming light (photon counts or flux) versus time. It shows how the brightness of a star changes over a period (called exposure time). Telescopes observe these light curves by continuously watching a star.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One fascinating use of light curves is to detect exoplanets. When a planet passes in front of its star (a transit), it causes a small dip in the light curve — and that’s how astronomers discover new worlds!&lt;br&gt;
Learn more about this method &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Methods_of_detecting_exoplanets#Transit_photometry&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;what-are-planet-spectra&#34;&gt;What Are Planet Spectra?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When telescopes use &lt;a href=&#34;https://noirlab.edu/public/blog/50-years-ccds/&#34;&gt;CCD detectors&lt;/a&gt;, they can measure not just when photons arrive, but also their &lt;strong&gt;energy&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;count&lt;/strong&gt;. Using this information, we can create a &lt;strong&gt;spectrum&lt;/strong&gt; of the planet — which is basically a plot of photon flux (or counts) vs &lt;strong&gt;wavelength&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This tells us what elements or molecules are present in the planet’s atmosphere. Want to go deeper? Check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://oxfordre.com/planetaryscience/display/10.1093/acrefore/9780190647926.001.0001/acrefore-9780190647926-e-134&#34;&gt;this article on planetary spectroscopy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;datasets-and-project-implementation&#34;&gt;Datasets and Project Implementation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dataset for this project came from the &lt;strong&gt;James Webb Space Telescope (JWST)&lt;/strong&gt; using its &lt;strong&gt;NIRSpec instrument&lt;/strong&gt;, specifically in &lt;strong&gt;Bright Object Time-Series (BOTS)&lt;/strong&gt; mode. For more details, visit the &lt;a href=&#34;https://jwst-docs.stsci.edu/jwst-near-infrared-spectrograph/nirspec-observing-modes/nirspec-bright-object-time-series-spectroscopy#gsc.tab=0&#34;&gt;official JWST documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The data was downloaded from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://mast.stsci.edu/portal/Mashup/Clients/Mast/Portal.html&#34;&gt;MAST Portal&lt;/a&gt; and came in &lt;strong&gt;FITS format&lt;/strong&gt;, which is the standard for astronomy data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project was done entirely in a &lt;strong&gt;Jupyter Notebook&lt;/strong&gt;, and here are some of the interesting visualizations I generated:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;light-curve-and-poisson-regression-fit&#34;&gt;Light Curve and Poisson Regression Fit&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/user-attachments/assets/98ce41e7-a80d-44f8-8ad1-bdd080a7919d&#34; alt=&#34;Light Curve Plot&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;transmission-spectroscopy&#34;&gt;Transmission Spectroscopy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When a planet transits, some starlight passes through its atmosphere. Different wavelengths of light are absorbed by atmospheric molecules, causing variations in the transit depth. Plotting these variations against wavelength produces a transmission spectrum, which reveals details about the atmosphere’s composition. For a clear explanation, watch this &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZnLg4YFMfDQ&amp;amp;ab_channel=MartianColonist&#34;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;transmission-spectrum-of-wasp-39b&#34;&gt;Transmission Spectrum of WASP-39b&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/user-attachments/assets/66baeb9c-f64f-4c27-a1e9-f8a0d4cc22d4&#34; alt=&#34;Transmission Spectrum&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The spectrum above shows how WASP-39b’s atmosphere affects light at different wavelengths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;detecting-atmospheric-composition&#34;&gt;Detecting Atmospheric Composition&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To determine the atmospheric composition, we use atmospheric retrieval. This involves comparing observed data to model spectra generated with known compositions. The model that best fits the data indicates the likely atmospheric makeup. For more insights, refer to this &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZnLg4YFMfDQ&amp;amp;ab_channel=MartianColonist&#34;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/user-attachments/assets/5efc277a-e584-465d-a986-0e71490eb463&#34; alt=&#34;Model Fit&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;composition-of-wasp-39bs-atmosphere&#34;&gt;Composition of WASP-39b’s Atmosphere&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a hot Jupiter, WASP-39b is expected to contain gases like methane and carbon dioxide. Analysis confirms the presence of water, sulfur dioxide, methane, and carbon dioxide. A distinct bump in the transmission spectrum between 4–5 µm confirms carbon dioxide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/user-attachments/assets/e8355d1c-d8f0-4439-9119-03fb3b6278e4&#34; alt=&#34;Molecular Contributions&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pressure-temperature-profile&#34;&gt;Pressure-Temperature Profile&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The retrieval process assumes a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.aanda.org/articles/aa/pdf/2010/12/aa13396-09.pdf&#34;&gt;Guillot pressure-temperature profile&lt;/a&gt; to model the atmosphere’s temperature structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/user-attachments/assets/dcdc5ea5-c144-445e-8c7c-2e1c59e9e020&#34; alt=&#34;Pressure-Temperature Profile&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;molecular-abundance&#34;&gt;Molecular Abundance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The abundance of molecules like water, methane, carbon dioxide, and sulfur dioxide varies with atmospheric pressure, as shown below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/user-attachments/assets/c709a606-6ba8-4fbd-9932-38365baae326&#34; alt=&#34;Pressure vs. Abundance&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transmission spectrum highlights specific absorption features for each molecule.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://github.com/user-attachments/assets/af1bfc59-19cb-4ed1-849d-48ad3108ddeb&#34; alt=&#34;Chemical Lines&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;REEFRENCES:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZnLg4YFMfDQ&#34;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZnLg4YFMfDQ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://petitradtrans.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&#34;&gt;https://petitradtrans.readthedocs.io/en/latest/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;project-repository&#34;&gt;Project Repository&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can check out the complete code and analysis on GitHub:&lt;br&gt;
👉 &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/Sauravroy34/JWST-light-curve-and-spectral-analysis&#34;&gt;JWST Light Curve and Planet Spectra&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Open Source Journey</title>
      <link>https://Sauravroy34.github.io/posts/my-open-source-journey/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 16:00:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://Sauravroy34.github.io/posts/my-open-source-journey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;my-open-source-journey&#34;&gt;My Open Source Journey&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been around &lt;strong&gt;8 months&lt;/strong&gt; since I started contributing to &lt;strong&gt;open source&lt;/strong&gt;, beginning with &lt;a href=&#34;https://openastronomy.org/&#34;&gt;OpenAstronomy&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;OpenAstronomy is an umbrella organization, and within it, I am an active contributor to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/sunpy/sunpy&#34;&gt;SunPy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/StingraySoftware/stingray&#34;&gt;Stingray Software&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;an-incredible-journey-so-far&#34;&gt;An Incredible Journey So Far&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This journey has been &lt;strong&gt;amazing&lt;/strong&gt;! I&amp;rsquo;ve had the opportunity to interact with incredible people—some are &lt;strong&gt;researchers&lt;/strong&gt;, some work at &lt;strong&gt;NASA&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;ESA&lt;/strong&gt;, and others are &lt;strong&gt;professors at top universities&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through open source, I&amp;rsquo;ve learned &lt;strong&gt;a lot&lt;/strong&gt; about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Computational Astronomy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Coding Standards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unit Testing with &lt;code&gt;pytest&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Documentation with &lt;code&gt;Sphinx&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pre-commit Hooks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;learned how to work with File formats like &lt;code&gt;FITS&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;ASDF&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the way i got into open source around september 2024 and journey has been amazing so far!!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My First Post</title>
      <link>https://Sauravroy34.github.io/posts/my-first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 15:57:50 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://Sauravroy34.github.io/posts/my-first-post/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi I am Saurav Kumar Roy a undergrad student from Amrita Viswa Vidyapeetham Amritapuri in India and This is my new blogging site. I will be posting my journey and experiences here. Enjoy!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>